Okay, moving on to the parathyroid gland.
Recall that the key cell within the parathyroid gland
is called the chief cell.
Its goal is to regulate the serum-free ionized calcium.
Remember that we're talking about free calcium,
and I emphasize that because 60% of the calcium
in your blood is bound to proteins,
so we're not worried about that.
And among the unbound calcium,
some of it is bound to phosphate.
We're also not worried about that.
This is going to regulate the free ionized calcium,
and the way by which it does it is by a PTH.
Now, when the free ionized calcium is low within the blood,
then PTH will be released,
and PTH acts on three major tissues in the body
to raise the calcium.
First, it will increase the activity of bone osteoclasts.
Now, recall that osteoclasts are the cells that resorb bone,
and so when they resorb bone,
both calcium and phosphate will be released into the blood.
Now, one high-yield point here
is that the PTH doesn't directly activate the osteoclast.
It actually activates the osteoblast,
which is the cell that lays down bone,
and once it activates the osteoblast,
the osteoblast then goes and activates the osteoclast,
and that's particularly high-yield to note.
So again, PTH activates the osteoblast,
which then in turn activates the osteoclast.
The osteoclast then resorbs bone,
releasing calcium and phosphate into the blood.
The second function of PTH
will be to increase small bowel absorption
of calcium and phosphate.
This is a little bit indirect.
Actually, PTH activates vitamin D,
then vitamin D then increases small bowel absorption
of calcium and phosphate.
And the third function of PTH
will be to grab calcium from the kidney
and to dump phosphate
so that you actually have decreased phosphate resorption.
So you'll grab calcium and dump phosphate.
This is a particularly noteworthy step
because by dumping the phosphate,
that's how you're going to really increase
the free ionized calcium.
Otherwise, this was bringing in both calcium and phosphate,
and this brought in both calcium and phosphate,
but you really want to increase the free ionized calcium.
And so this, again, is a very important function.
Now, the first disorder of the parathyroid
is primary hyperparathyroidism.
This is where you have excess parathyroid hormone
due to a disorder of the parathyroid gland itself.
Now, you can actually get primary hyperparathyroidism
in three ways.
You can get an adenoma,
which would be a tumor that's going to produce
too much parathyroid hormone.
You could have a sporadic hyperplasia
where the cells just hyperplase for an unknown reason.
That could also result in too much parathyroid hormone.
And the third possibility would be carcinoma.
You could get a parathyroid carcinoma,
which would then produce too much PTH.
However, the most common cause is parathyroid adenoma.
Parathyroid adenoma, again, is a benign neoplasm,
usually involving one gland.
It will produce PTH,
and that PTH will then, of course,
raise the serum calcium.
However, it's usually asymptomatic.
If, however, symptoms are present,
they will be based on the consequences of increased PTH
and on the consequences of hypercalcemia.
For example, if patients have hypercalcemia in the blood,
there's going to be a high filtration of calcium
into the urine,
and so patients can develop kidney stones
or nephrolithiasis,
and the classic kidney stone
would be a calcium oxalate stone.
So this would be one example
of a consequence of hypercalcemia.
Another consequence of hypercalcemia
would be that when you have high levels of calcium
within the blood, you increase the risk
for deposition of calcium on tissues,
which is called metastatic calcification.
The classic example of metastatic calcification
is called nephrocalcinosis,
where you deposit calcium in the tubules of the kidney.
This can lead to renal insufficiency with polyuria,
and so it's another consequence of hypercalcemia.
In addition, the hypercalcemia can go into the CNS
and cause CNS disturbances,
such as depression and seizures.
Hypercalcemia can also lead to constipation,
peptic ulcer disease, and acute pancreatitis.
This is particularly high-yield hypercalcemia
producing an acute pancreatitis.
The way I remember it is that if you have high calcium,
high calcium is sort of an enzyme activator,
and so you can activate the enzymes of the pancreas
within the pancreas,
giving you an acute pancreatitis.
And finally, because you've got high levels of PTH,
you're gonna have massive resorption of bone.
You can eventually produce fibrosis and cysts
within the bone,
which is called osteitis fibrosa cystica.
Now here is a picture of the kidney
showing the tubules of the kidney,
and you can clearly see that there's deposition of calcium
within some of these tubules,
and so this is an example of metastatic calcification
in a patient with hypercalcemia,
and of course, this would then be called nephrocalcinosis.
An additional consequence would be
to get fibrosis of the bone,
and so here you can see this is clearly a spicule of bone,
and you've got this dense fibrosis,
and sometimes you can see cysts and hemorrhage as well,
and that's called osteitis fibrosa cystica,
again, a consequence of the high PTH.
The lab findings in primary hyperparathyroidism
will be a high serum PTH.
Of course, the adenoma, for example, is making PTH.
You'll have a high serum calcium,
but a decreased serum phosphate.
Of course, the high serum calcium is due to the fact
that you're resorbing bone,
increasing absorption from the gut,
and also increasing resorption from the kidney,
and the low serum phosphate is due to the fact
that you have decreased resorption in the kidney,
or you're quote-unquote dumping phosphate into the urine.
You can also have an increased urinary cyclic AMP.
This is very high yield for the board exam,
so let me just review this physiology briefly.
Remember that if this is the cell
that's responding to the PTH,
then you've sort of got this receptor here,
and PTH will bind this receptor.
Let's, for example, take the kidney.
Now, when PTH binds the tubular cells of the kidney,
then that is going to be coupled
to a G-stimulatory protein.
That G-stimulatory protein will activate
adenylate cyclase, very high yield,
and that adenylate cyclase will then convert ATP
into cyclic AMP,
and so cyclic AMP will then mediate the effects of the PTH,
and so cyclic AMP can be increased in the urine
because you've got this PTH,
which is hitting the tubules,
and so you've got increased cyclic AMP
within the tubular cells,
which can then get into the urine.
Very high yield for the purposes of board exams
because it takes you back
to a little bit of normal physiology,
which they love to tie in.
Finally, the patients can have an increase
in the serum alkaline phosphatase,
and this is a particularly high yield point as well.
Now, alkaline phosphatase is an enzyme
that actually generates an alkaline environment
in the region of the bone,
and the alkaline environment is necessary
to lay down calcium on bone.
And so you could ask the question,
why is there an increase in the alkaline phosphatase
when you're actually resorbing bone
and actually removing calcium?
Well, the answer is that remember
that the PTH doesn't directly activate the osteoclast.
It actually activates the osteoblast,
which is going to lay down bone,
and at the same time turn on the osteoclast,
which will eat up bone.
And so the osteoblast is actually going to be turned on.
It's going to lay down bone,
and when it lays down bone,
it actually produces alkaline phosphatase.
So the alkaline phosphatase is actually a sign
of osteoblastic activity,
and that's because, of course,
the PTH receptors are on the osteoblast,
so that becomes high yield as well.
The treatment is surgical removal of the affected gland,
and so, for example, if there's an adenoma,
you'll simply remove that adenoma.
Secondary hyperparathyroidism
is when you have excess production of PTH.
However, it's due to a disease process
that is extrinsic to the parathyroid gland,
i.e. there is some other disease process
that results in the overproduction of PTH.
The most common cause is chronic renal failure.
The idea here is that when you have renal failure,
you're going to have decreased excretion of phosphate.
Phosphate will then build up in the blood.
Phosphate loves to bind free calcium,
and so phosphate will bind free calcium,
therefore the free calcium levels will decrease.
Now remember that the parathyroid gland
doesn't look at anything except free calcium,
and so when it sees that there's less free calcium,
that's going to stimulate all four parathyroid glands
to increase PTH secretion,
and that then will result in a secondary hyperparathyroidism.
The lab findings will be an increase in PTH,
and they'll have a decrease in their serum calcium.
Why?
Because remember that this process is driven
by the fact that there's high phosphate,
and when there's high phosphate,
the serum calcium will actually be low,
and so there'll be a low serum calcium
and an increased serum phosphate.
At the same time,
there'll be a high alkaline phosphatase,
and why is there a high alkaline phosphatase?
Because the PTH is hitting the bone,
in particular the osteoblasts,
and so the osteoblasts are overactive,
and so you've got a high alkaline phosphatase.
Moving on to hypoparathyroidism,
this is when you have a low PTH.
The causes include autoimmune damage,
you can have autoimmune destruction
of the parathyroid glands,
surgical excision,
for example if the patient has removal of a thyroid
and the parathyroid gets taken by accident,
or for example if there is parathyroid hyperplasia
and the parathyroids are removed.
And finally, DeGeorge syndrome.
Remember in DeGeorge syndrome you get failure to develop
the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch,
and of course the parathyroid are also a derivative
of the third and fourth pharyngeal pouch.
The presentation would be based on the fact
that there would be a low serum-free calcium,
and so you'd get numbness and tingling,
that's a very early sign,
particularly perioral around the lips,
and then they can also get muscle spasms,
and the classic examples of this would be the Trousseau sign,
where you feel the blood pressure cuff
on the patient's arm and you get muscle spasms,
or you could get Chosevic's sign where you tap
on the facial nerve and also get muscle spasms.
Pseudohypoparathyroidism is when you have
the signs and symptoms of hypoparathyroidism,
however it is not due to a problem with the parathyroid,
instead it is due to a problem with the organs
not responding to PTH.
And so in this particular case you'll have hypocalcemia,
however the PTH levels will be high,
and that's because the parathyroid is making PTH.
Now particularly high yield to note,
and sometimes asked on board examinations,
and that is that the end organ resistance here
is actually due to a defect in the G-stimulatory protein.
Again, this goes back to our normal diagram,
if this was the cell and this was the receptor for PTH,
again when PTH binds it's associated with a G-protein,
and particularly there's a G-stimulatory protein here.
This G-stimulatory protein will then turn on adenylate cyclase,
and of course when you turn on adenylate cyclase,
that helps to take ATP to generate cyclic AMP,
which is a key messenger.
Now what happens in one subtype of pseudo-hypoparathyroidism
is that you have a defective GS protein here,
and that's particularly high yield board examiners
love to go after it because it's really a way
by which they can test you on normal physiology.
Now in that particular subtype of pseudo-hypoparathyroidism,
it's an autosomal dominant form,
and it's also associated with short stature
and short fourth and fifth digits.
So that's a high yield association as well,
particularly for board examinations.
And that concludes our section on parathyroid.